Cell: 515-249-6638

Email: putz.austin@gmail.com

AUSTIN PUTZ

Curriculum Vitae

PERSONAL SUMMARY

Austin grew up on a diversified family farm where he helped manage 600 acres that included row crops, cattle, horses, and pigs among others species. As an undergraduate student at Iowa State University he worked in several molecular genetic labs to gain an understanding of molecular biology before moving to quantitative genetics. Internships with Fast Genetics and Smithfield Premium Genetics have been valuable as a future professional in the field. At North Carolina State University he has focused on learning numerous technical skills (e.g. R, Unix/Linux, SAS, Python, and LaTeX) along with basic quantitative genetics and animal breeding. He has already completed five graduate level statistics courses that have given him an advantage in data analysis. His goal is to complete his Master's degree in the Spring of 2015 and begin his PhD in the Fall of 2015 after completing another internship next summer.

EDUCATION

Master of Science

May 2015 (expected) Raleigh, NC

North Carolina State University

Major: Animal Breeding and Genetics

Minor: Statistics

GPA: 4.0

Bachelor of Science

May 2013 Ames, IA

Iowa State University Major: Animal Science Summa Cum Lauda

GPA: 3.93

COMPUTER

Advanced: R, Unix/Linux

Intermediate: LaTeX, SAS, BLUPF90 Programs

Beginner: Python, DMU Programs

WORK EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant

Aug 2013 - Present

North Carolina State University

Raleigh, NC

Master's degree started in the fall of 2013 working with Smithfield Premium Genetics data. Worked on a new trait, litter size at day 5, for their maternal line indexes.

Research and Development Intern

Summer 2013/2014 Rose Hill, NC

Smithfield Premium Genetics

Full-time intern summer 2013. Part-time summer 2014.

- Data management
- Variance component estimation
- ◆ GWAS
- Accuracy comparison
- Collected carcass traits in packing plant
- Assisted in data collection for growth curve study
- Final presentation

Research Assistant

Aug 2012 – May 2013

Swine Molecular Genetics Lab

Ames, IA

Worked for Dr. Chris Tuggle on 2 projects. 1) Prepared RNA samples for subsequent RNA-Seq analysis on the residual feed intake grant and 2) assisted in the development of allelespecific PCR procedures to genotype SNPs associated with PRRS.

- ◆ DNA/RNA isolation
- Created cDNA
- PCR and qPCR
- NanoDrop for concentrations
- Bioanalyzer for RNA quality

Breeding and Farrowing Technician

May 2012 – Aug 2012

Fast Genetics

Cando, ND

6,000-head sow multiplying unit in North Dakota. Half the summer was spent as a breeding technician and the second half was spent in farrowing.

- Artificially inseminated main line sows and gilts
- Gave shots
- Daily feeding and observation
- Managed data
- Induced sows and gilts
- Delivered piglets

Lab Assistant

Jan 2012 – May 2012

Beef Molecular Genetics Lab

Ames, IA

Worked for Dr. James Reecy as a lab assistant.

- Data collection on farm and in packing plants
- Basic data management
- NanoDrop
- Basic lab chores

Lab Assistant

May 2011 – Dec 2011 Ames, IA

Soils Microbiology Lab

- Micro-balanced
- Sampled soil and gas
- Processed soil
- Ran enzyme analyses
- Managed data
- Basic lab chores

Barn Crew Member

Aug 2010 – May 2011

Iowa State University Veterinary School

Ames, IA

- Strict biosecurity
- Maintained horse wards, bovine, ICU, and isolation
- Disinfected stalls after animal departure
- Regular maintenance of stalls

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

Jan 2014 – April 2014

North Carolina State University

Raleigh, NC

Teaching assistant for the undergraduate reproductive physiology class under Dr. Whisnant.

- Set up labs
- Assisted in teaching
- Lectured genetic improvement lab
- Checked weekly assignments and guizzes

Organic Chemistry Tutor

Jan 2012 – May 2012

Iowa State University

Ames, IA

Tutored two students in Chem 331.

- Reviewed class notes
- Solved review problems together
- Helped review for exams

REFEREED JOURNALS

Putz, A. M., K. A. Gray, C. Maltecca, F. Tiezzi, and M. T. Knauer. 2014. Variance component estimates for alternative litter size and piglet mortality traits in swine. J. Anim. Sci. In preparation.

ABSTRACTS

Putz, A. M., K. A. Gray, M. T. Knauer. Variance component estimates for alternative litter size and piglet mortality traits. 2014. Presented orally at ASAS Midwestern Section.

PROJECTS

man pages for BLUPF90 programs

Developed Unix/Linux based man (manual) pages for the BLUPF90 family of programs. This allows new and old users a way of accessing documentation from within a terminal window. Additional information was added for things not

documented precisely by the UGA group.

vim syntax highlighting for BLUPF90 programs

Created a basic syntax-highlighting file for use with the BLUPF90 family of programs. This will allow users to easily identify mistakes that could be extremely detrimental to running variance components or genomic analyses.

HONORS Lane Wells Scholarship August 2011

Iowa State University Ames, IA

Kenneth and Ruth Wagner Scholarship August 2012

Iowa State University Ames, IA

Arthur Molln Scholarship August 2012

Iowa State University Ames, IA

National Pork Board Scholarship April 2013
National Pork Board Clive, IA

\$3,500 as the second ranked applicant in the 2013 pool.

SHORT COURSES Programming and computer algorithms in animal breeding with

focus on genomic selection and single-step GBLUP

University of Georgia May 2014

REFERENCES Dr. Mark Knauer

North Carolina State University

Assistant Professor

Master's Committee Chair Phone: 919-515-8797

Email: mtknauer@ncsu.edu

Dr. Kent Gray

Smithfield Premium Genetics

Director of Research and Development

Master's Committee Member

Phone: 910-282-4227

Email: kent.gray@spgenetics.com

Dr. Chris Tuggle

Iowa State University

Professor

Phone: 515-294-4252

Email: cktuggle@iastate.edu

Dr. Tom Baas

Iowa State University

Professor Phone: 515-294-6728

Email: tjbaas@iastate.edu